# RICHARD J. NUGENT III

365 Fifth Avenue, New York, NY 10016

(847) 736-2597 \$\phi\$ richard.nugent.3@gmail.com \$\phi\$ sites.google.com/view/richardnugent

## **PROFILE**

My dissertation documents the economic consequences of barriers to international capital markets. The methods involved in my research include panel data analysis using fixed effects, instrumental variables, and Arellano-Bond GMM. I also use quasi-experimental methods including the synthetic control method, difference-in-difference, and elastic net regularization as an effective solution to the endogeneity problem. I find new evidence that barriers to international capital markets can have unintended consequences for international lending and private credit.

## **EDUCATION**

The Graduate Center, City University of New York, New York, NY

Ph.D., Economics, Expected May 2019

M.A., Economics, May 2018

Specializations: Financial Economics, Public Finance, Applied Econometrics

Select Coursework: Quantitative Macroeconomics, Macroeconometrics, Corporate Finance, Big Data Analytics

The University of Illinois at Chicago, Chicago, IL

B.A., Economics, May 2012

Chicago Civic Leadership Certificate, May 2010

## **SKILLS**

Modeling Generalized Linear Models, Panel Data, Time Series, Potential Outcomes (DiD, Elastic

Net, Multivariate Matching, Propensity Score, SCM), Partial Equilibrium Simulation

**Programming** GAMS, MATLAB, Python, R, SQL

Software & Tools Eviews, LATEX, Mathematica, MS Office Suite, Stata, Tableau

Languages English (Native), Spanish (Fully Proficient)

## **EXPERIENCE**

## Department of Economics, Hunter College, CUNY, New York, NY

Adjunct Lecturer, January 2014 - Present

- · Taught a large portfolio of economics courses to over 1300 Hunter College students over six years.
- · Tasked with teaching large format sections (enrollment of up to 140 students), requiring extensive use of Microsoft PowerPoint in the design of digital assets.

## Office of Economics, US International Trade Commission, Washington DC

Economist Trainee, June 2017 - August 2017/May 2018 - August 2018

- · Used matching econometrics to analyze the influence of non-tariff measures on international trade using Python.
- · Simulated industry-specific economic shocks using a partial equilibrium Armington framework in the steel and coal industries using the General Algebraic Modeling System (**GAMS**) software.
- · Published a comprehensive literature review on measures of trade in value-added and their policy implications in USITC Economics Working Paper "An Overview on the Construction of the North American Regional Supply-Use and Input-Output Tables and their Applications in Policy Analysis."
- · Collected, cleaned, and organized large data sets in **Stata** for use in regression analysis.

## Economic Studies Group (ESG), New York, NY

Advanced Research Collaborative Fellow, Contributor, August 2017 - August 2018

- · Published a primer on the role that rules of origin played in the renegotiation of NAFTA (USMCA).
- · Contributed to ESG policy analyses by generating original data visualization using R.

## PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

"Restrictions on Short-term Capital Inflows and the Response of Direct Investment" (Forthcoming) Eastern Economic Journal, 2018.

## ACADEMIC AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Provost's Office University Fellowship (2018), Teaching and Learning Center Mini Grant (2017), Advanced Research Collaborative Fellowship (2017), Sallie Mae Student Fellowship Award (2015)